Finding Aid for Vladimir Dedijer papers, 1881-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Vladimir Dedijer papers 1881-1987, 1940-1980
Dedijer, Vladimir, 1914-1990.
1 oversize volume
9.5 linear feet
92119 Aa 2
Yugoslavian author and scholar, member of the Communist Party of Yugoslavia (CPY), participant in the partisan army during the Yugoslav Revolution of the 1940s, acquaintance of such Yugoslav leaders as Tito and Milovan Djilas. Series in the collection include biographical/personal, Dedijer family, correspondence, topical files, Bertrand Russell War Crimes Tribunals, project files, writings, lectures and speeches, audio and visual materials, and printed material; include correspondence with various intellectuals and political figures; subjects in the collection concern Yugoslav history, particularly Dedijer's relationship with Tito and Milovan Djilas; also materials relating to the International War Crimes Tribunal investigating United States involvement in Vietnam.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Vladimir Dedijer (Donor No. 7163 ) in five accessions beginning in 1985.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Vladimir Dedijer, a Yugoslav author and scholar, was a Visiting Professor of History at the University of Michigan three times during the 1970s. He is known best for his writings on Yugoslav history, most notably his biography of Marshall Josip Broz (Tito) and his war diaries of his experiences as a member of the partisan army during the Yugoslav Revolution.
Dedijer was born in Belgrade in 1914 to Jevto and Milica Dedijer. His father was a professor of geography at Belgrade University. His mother, a social worker, was actively involved in the women's liberation movement in Yugoslavia.
Dedijer became active in international affairs at an early age, attending the Conference for Reconciliation in Poland in 1929 as a delegate of Yugoslav high school youth. In 1931, he attended the XX World Congress of the Young Men's Christian Association in Cleveland, Ohio. Following high school, Dedijer worked for the daily newspaper Politika while studying law. He received his Doctorate of Philosophy in Law from Belgrade University in 1956. As a journalist he served as a foreign correspondent in Poland, Denmark, Norway (1935), England (1935-1936), and Spain (1936). He was fired from Politika in 1937 by order of the Yugoslav government for supporting the Republican government in Spain during the Spanish Civil War. From 1937 to 1941 Dedijer worked in various positions at a number of underground publications.
During the early 1930s Dedijer had begun forming ties with the Communist Party of Yugoslavia (CPY). In 1937 he made the acquaintance of such influential Yugoslav Communist leaders as Tito, Edvard Kardelj, Milovan Djilas, and Aleksandar Rankovic. The CPY had existed in Yugoslavia for many years despite being outlawed in 1920 and was under the control of the Soviet Union. Tito had been a member of the CPY since 1920 and was imprisoned as a result of his communist activity from 1928 to 1934. Following his release from prison, Tito became a member of the Central Committee of the CPY, then of the Politburo, and finally, in 1937, assumed leadership of the party.
In April 1941 Germany invaded Yugoslavia. The country of Yugoslavia was created at the end of World War I, but tensions among its diverse ethnic population remained strong; therefore, the reaction of Yugoslavia and its people to the Axis invasion varied greatly. Tito and his partisan forces determined to fight the Germans and those Yugoslav units that supported Hitler. The division in the country was in fact a civil war -- the Yugoslav Revolution -- that was not resolved until the victory of Tito and his forces in 1945.
Dedijer joined Tito and the partisans in 1941 in their struggle against the Axis forces and served as Lieutenant Colonel in Tito's headquarters. It was during this period that Dedijer began keeping his diaries of the war, published by the University of Michigan Press in 1990 and described as "the most detailed and important source about Yugoslavia and the partisans in World War II" (John Fine, Introduction to War Diaries, p. xv).
During the next ten years Dedijer rose among the political ranks of the CPY, holding a variety of appointments and positions. In April 1945 he was a member of the Yugoslav delegation to the United Nations and also attended the General Assemblies of the United Nations in 1946, 1948, 1951, and 1952. He attended the Paris Peace Conference in 1946 as a member of the Yugoslav delegation. Dedijer was appointed to the Yugoslav Parliament in 1953 and served as chairman of the foreign relations committee.
In early 1954, Dedijer's friend and comrade Milovan Djilas was dismissed from his positions as Vice President of Yugoslavia and president of the Parliament for making statements in the press critical of the communist government. Dedijer defended Djilas' freedom of expression before the Central Committee of the CPY in January 1954, and thus was expelled from the CPY, removed from his political offices, and dismissed from his teaching position in the History Department at the University of Belgrade. Both men were found guilty of criminal charges at a secret trial in January 1955. Djilas received a three year jail sentence. Dedijer received a six-month suspended sentence, however the verdict continued to have severe consequences on both his personal and professional life for the next five years.
By 1960 Dedijer was permitted to commence lecturing abroad and in the following years held various academic posts in Sweden, England, and the United States. He also became acquainted with and corresponded with such intellectuals and activists as Bertrand Russell, Jean Paul Sartre, Simone de Beauvoir, G.D.H. Cole, Noam Chomsky, Eleanor Roosevelt, and many others. As a result of these contacts Dedijer became actively involved with the Bertrand Russell Peace Foundation and its War Crimes Tribunals.
The Bertrand Russell War Crimes Tribunal was co-founded by Bertrand Russell and Jean Paul Sartre in 1966. Its original purpose was to examine the activities of the United States in Vietnam. The members of the Tribunal included Jean Paul Sartre as Executive President, Dedijer as Chairman and President of Tribunal sessions, and other notable figures as Simone de Beauvoir, Lazaro Cardenas, Stokely Carmichael, and Dave Dellinger. The purpose of the Tribunal was later expanded to investigate acts of aggression and human rights violations committed by any country.
Dedijer's writings are numerous; his articles and reviews have been published in many scholarly publications, and he has written a number of books on the history of Yugoslavia and its people. Tito Speaks, the authorized biography of Marshall Josip Broz, was published in 1952, significant for Tito's narrative recollections of the break with Stalin in 1948. The Beloved Land (1961) is an autobiographical account of Yugoslav history beginning with Dedijer's ancestors. The Road to Sarajevo (1966) reexamines the origins of World War I, throwing new light on the people and events surrounding the assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand. Published in 1971, The Battle Stalin Lost describes Stalin's unsuccessful attempts to depose Tito after the CPY was kicked out of the Comintern and the reactions of Yugoslav communists to Stalinist policies.
With respect to his family, Dedijer was married twice and had five children. His first wife, Olga Popovic, was a field surgeon for the partisans and was killed in 1943 during the Yugoslav Revolution at the battle of Sutjeska Canyon. Dedijer was remarried in 1944 to Vera Krizman, an actress who had been imprisoned for writing anti-fascist graffiti on houses. He and Vera had five children: two daughters, Bojana and Milica, and three sons, Borivoje ("Boro"), Branimir ("Branko"), and Marko. Vladimir Dedijer died on November 30, 1990, in New York.
The papers of Vladimir Dedijer measure 9 linear feet plus one outsize volume and date from 1881 to 1987. The bulk of the materials cover the years 1940 to 1987. The papers include both materials created by Vladimir Dedijer during his life as a lecturer, author, and political figure, and also materials collected by Dedijer in his research relating to the history of Yugoslavia and communism. Many languages are represented in these papers, yet the majority of the materials are in English, Serbian, or Croatian.
The papers of Vladimir Dedijer are divided into ten series: Biographical/Personal Materials, Dedijer Family, Correspondence, Topical Files, Bertrand Russell War Crimes Tribunals, Project Files, Miscellaneous Writings, Lectures and Speeches, Audio and Visual Materials, and Printed Materials.
Subjects:
Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-1973; Authors, Yugoslav.; Beauvoir, Simone de, 1908-1986.; Chomsky, Noam.; Cole, G. D. H. (George Douglas Howard), 1889-1959.; Dedijer, Vladimir.; Djilas, Milovan, 1911-1995.; Hellman, Lillian, 1905-1984.; International War Crimes Tribunal.; Paris Peace Conference (1946); Revolutionary literature, Yugoslav.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970.; Sartre, Jean Paul, 1905-1980.; Sulzberger, C. L. (Cyrus Leo), 1912-1993.; Tito, Josip Broz, 1892-1980.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Welles, Orson, 1915-1985.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia--History--1918-1945.; Yugoslavia--History--1945-1980.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
International War Crimes Tribunal.; Paris Peace Conference (1946); Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970.; Sartre, Jean Paul, 1905-1980.; Tito, Josip Broz, 1892-1980.; Yugoslavia.
Contributors
Anders, Günther, 1892-1992.; Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-1973; Barnes, Joseph.; Beauvoir, Simone de, 1908-1986.; Chomsky, Noam.; Cole, G. D. H. (George Douglas Howard), 1889-1959.; Deakin, F. W. (Frederick William), 1913-2005.; Dellinger, David T., 1915-2004.; Fast, Howard, 1914-2003.; Haley, William, Sir, 1901-; Hellman, Lillian, 1905-1984.; Lash, Joseph P., 1909-1987.; Lee, Jennie, 1904-; Maclean, Fitzroy, 1911-1996.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Sartre, Jean Paul, 1905-1980.; Shirer, William L. (William Lawrence), 1904-1993.; Sulzberger, C. L. (Cyrus Leo), 1912-1993.; Welles, Orson, 1915-1985.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal Materials
  The Biographical/Personal Materials series (1.3 linear feet) consists of such materials as Dedijer's curriculum vitae, newsclippings, interview transcripts, and diaries and calendars. The extensive newsclippings, provide a good overview of Dedijer's activities throughout his life.
  - General 1953-1979, undated (Box 1)
  - Attacks against Dedijer
    - From Moscow 1948-1953 (Box 1)
    - Other 1943, 1951-1953, 1983 undated (Box 1)
  - Diaries and Calendars
    - Diaries of Vladimir Dedijer
      - 1946 Paris Peace Conference
        - General (Box 1)
        - Notes on sessions (Box 1)
        - Work in commissions (Box 1)
      - February-April 1948, India (Box 1)
      - March 1953-September 1954, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - August 1954-September 1956, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1956-1957, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1956-1959, Miscellaneous additions to diary (Box 1)
      - May-June 1969 September 1969 (Box 1)
      - 1980, Tehran (Box 1)
      - Daily Calendars
        - 1953 (Box 1)
        - 1958 1959 (Box 1)
        - 1971 (Box 1)
  - Interviews with Dedijer
    - General
      - In English 1943, 1951, 1954, 1961, 1964, 1971, 1987 undated (Box 1)
      - In other languages 1954, 1960-1971, 1981 undated (Box 1)
    - Faked interview with Dedijer (appeared in Bild-Telegraf newspaper, October 15, 1957), 1957-1971 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings about Dedijer
    - In English 1951-1974, 1982-1984, undated (Box 2)
    - In other languages 1951-1985, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Passports, address books, etc., 19 small items (in 1 expandable folder) (Box 2)
- Dedijer Family
  The Dedijer Family series (0.3 linear feet) is also biographical in nature and includes Dedijer's correspondence with his family members.
  - General 1923-1960, undated (Box 2)
    (includes photos)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - Undated (Box 2)
      - 1944-1955 (Box 2)
      - 1956-1959 (Box 2)
      - 1971-1974 (mostly from Vera Dedijer) (Box 2)
    - Milica Dedijer (daughter) 1959-1980, undated (Box 2)
    - Steve Dedijer (brother) 1952-1959, undated (includes photos) (Box 2)
  - Deaths of Boro and Branko Dedijer, Investigation of 1959-1981, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Family finance book 1954-1959 (Box 2)
  - Monument to Olga Dedijer 1953-1956 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1937-1985
  The Correspondence series (0.4 linear feet) is divided into two subseries, "In English" and "In Other Languages", the latter composed mostly of letters in Serbian and Croatian. Correspondence is arranged chronologically within each subseries and includes both chatty, personal letters as well as intellectual discussions of contemporary political issues. Located in this series are Dedijer's letters to and from such notables as Eleanor Roosevelt, Orson Welles, Lillian Hellman, and Simone de Beauvoir. Other noteworthy correspondents include Noam Chomsky, Hamilton Fish Armstrong, C.L. Sulzberger, G.D.H. Cole, and George Seldes.
  Regarding additional correspondence in other series, the Topical Files series includes correspondence with Milovan Djilas, G.D.H. Cole, and Arlette and Jean-Paul Sartre; the Bertrand Russell War Crimes Tribunals series includes correspondence with Bertrand Russell, Arlette and Jean Paul Sartre, and other Tribunal members; the Project Files series includes correspondence with Orson Welles and Jean Paul Sartre; and the Scrapbook within the Printed Materials series contains letters from Louis Adamic, Eleanor Roosevelt, and Tito. While many letters are of substantial length, much of the correspondence with famous figures is of autograph value only.
  - By Date
    - Undated 1945-1985, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - By Name
    - Anders, Günther (Box 10)
    - Armstrong, Hamilton Fish (Box 10)
    - Barnes, Joseph and Betty (Box 10)
      (also includes Jean Highland)
    - Chomsky, Noam (Box 10)
    - Deakin, William (Box 10)
    - Dellinger, David (Box 10)
    - Eek, Hilding (Box 10)
    - Eichler, Willi (Box 10)
    - Fast, Howard (Box 10)
    - Friedman, W. (Director, International Legal Research) (Box 10)
    - Haley, Sir William (Box 10)
    - Hellman, Lillian (Box 10)
    - Hinden, Rita (Box 10)
    - Hughes, Stuart (Box 10)
    - Lash, Joseph P. (Box 10)
    - Lee, Jennie (Box 10)
    - Maclean, Sir Fitzroy (Box 10)
    - Monsen, Per (Box 10)
    - Pejou, Marcel (Box 10)
    - Pollak, Oscar (Box 10)
    - Rohde, Ina and Petar (Box 10)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Box 10)
    - Ross, A. (Box 10)
    - Salisbury, Harrison E. (Box 10)
    - Shirer, William (Box 10)
    - Silvers, Robert E. (Box 10)
    - Thomas, Norman (Box 10)
    - Welles, Orson (Box 10)
  - In Other Languages
    - 1937, 1944-1959 (Box 10)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 10)
    - 1970-1974, 1983, 1985 (Box 10)
    - undated (Simone de Beauvoir) (Box 10)
    - Dedijer's letters to Tito 1954, 1959 (Box 10)
- Topical Files 1941-1980
  Most notable within the Topical Files series (1.0 linear feet) are the materials relating to Milovan Djilas and to Jean Paul Sartre. The Djilas materials are divided into two groups, the first being materials relating to the trial. Here are Djilas' correspondence with Dedijer, detailed materials regarding Djilas' criticism of the government, Dedijer's support of Djilas, the trial of Djilas, and the resulting effects on the lives of Dedijer and Djilas and their families. Also of interest in this series are the materials regarding Jean Paul Sartre which include correspondence, newsclippings, and notes relating to various projects he and Dedijer developed and worked on together.
  - Belgrade University 1950-1954 (Box 3)
  - Communist Party of India 1947-1948, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Course Syllabi (from courses taught) 1971, 1974, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Djilas, Milovan
    - Trial
      - General 1953-1955, 1957 (Box 3)
      - Dedijer's defense of Djilas 1954 (Box 3)
      - Press statement of Dedijer (undelivered) December 1954 (Box 3)
      - My Two Comrades by Dedijer, 1957 (Box 3)
      - Newsclippings 1954 January-May, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Other
      - Article on British invasion of Greece by Dedijer with corrections by Djilas 1944 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence with Dedijer 1952, 1961-1969, undated (Box 3)
      - French Communist Party 1947 (Box 3)
      - Newsclippings
        - In English 1954-1964 (Box 3)
        - In other languages 1956-1964 (Box 3)
      - Research materials collected by Dedijer for book about Djilas 1950-1972 (Box 3)
      - Speech 1951 (Box 3)
      - Stalin meeting notes 1944 (Box 3)
  - Guild Socialism and G.D.H. Cole 1951-1960, undated (Box 3)
  - Kardelj, Edvard 1941-1943, 1951, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Kostic, Milica (poetry) undated (Box 3)
  - Militarism 1953-1961 (Box 3)
  - Rankovic, Aleksander 1957-1959 (Box 3)
  - Sartre, Jean Paul
    - General 1968-1980 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1967-1980, undated (Box 3)
  - Socialism in Western Europe: Poland, Germany, Denmark 1959-1965 (Box 3)
  - Stalin and Yugoslavia 1948-1951, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Sulzberger, C.L. and The Resistentialists (includes correspondence with Eleanor Roosevelt), 1952-1969 (Box 3)
  - Tito (Marshall Josip Broz)
    - General 1952, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Comintern 1941-1943 (Box 4)
    - Cominform and 1948 break with Stalin, 1948-1951 (Box 4)
    - Proposal for Nobel Peace Prize 1973 (Box 4)
  - Yugoslav Parliament 1953 (Box 4)
- Bertrand Russell War Crimes Tribunals
  The majority of the materials in the Bertrand Russell War Crimes Tribunals series (1.3 linear feet) are from the 1967 investigative hearings of the Tribunal regarding the crimes allegedly committed by the United States against Vietnam. The supporting Documents and Reports reviewed by the Tribunal members during the hearings comprise the bulk of the materials. The Documents and Reports also include transcripts of testimony heard by the Tribunal members during the hearings. The remainder of the materials focus on subsequent investigations by the Tribunal, such as the investigation in 1986-1987 regarding the World War II activities of Kurt Waldheim, former president of Austria. This series also contains materials relating to organizations similar to the Bertrand Russell Peace Foundation.
  - General Materials and Other Investigations
    - General 1968-1987, undated (Box 4)
    - Bohinj International Committee for the Investigation of Repression by Police, Army, and Tribunals 1971, undated (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1966-1971, undated (Box 4)
    - Investigations of alleged crimes (by countries other than the United States) 1968-1987, undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Newsclippings 1966-1983 (Box 4)
    - Stockholm Conference on Czechoslovakia 1969 (Box 4)
    - Waldheim, Kurt, Investigation regarding 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - United States' War Crimes in Viet-Nam, Investigation of (alleged)
    - General
      - Brussels meeting 1967 September 20 (Box 4)
      - Centre International d'Information pour la Denonciation des Crimes de Guerre 1969, undated (Box 4)
      - Documents and reports (Box 4)
      - Genocide 1967, 1970 (Box 4)
      - Handwritten notes from sessions 1967 (Box 4)
      - Japan Committee for the Investigation of US War Crimes in Vietnam (includes reports of Tokyo Tribunal on US Crimes of Aggression and War in Viet-Nam 1967 August 28-30, and one photo), 1967-1968, undated (Box 4)
      - Publication of book on first session 1967, undated (Box 4)
      - Stockholm Conference on Viet-Nam 1968 June-1970 June (Box 4)
      - Tribunal members: biographies and statements (Box 4)
      - Vietnamese Commission for Investigation of the US Imperialists' War Crimes in Vietnam 1967-1970 (Box 4)
    - First Session (Stockholm 1967 May 2-10)
      - Documents and reports
        - In English, 5 folders (Box 4)
        - In French, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Reaction of Sweden (Box 4)
    - Second Session (Roskilde 1967 November 20-December 1)
      - Chronological Files
        - 1967
          - November 17-30, 1967, 4 folders (Box 4)
          - November 17-30, 1967, 8 folders (Box 5)
          - December 1967 (Box 5)
      - Documents and reports
        - In English, 3 folders (Box 5)
        - In French, 3 folders (Box 5)
- Project Files
  The Project Files series (1.5 linear feet) contains research and other materials relating to Dedijer's major projects and is divided into two subseries: Film and Television Projects, and Books. Within each subseries, projects are generally arranged alphabetically by the name of the film or publication. Types of materials found here for films include newsclippings, correspondence, and drafts of scripts; and, for books, outlines, drafts, research materials, book reviews, and correspondence. Within the research materials for Sarajevo 1914 are the unpublished book manuscripts of Dragisa Stojadinovic.
  - Film and Television Projects
    - General 1952-1953, 1968-1971, undated (Box 5)
    - Battle of Sutjeska, 1968-1970, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - The Road to Sarajevo
      - August 1966-June 1967 with director Sveta Lukic (Box 5)
      - June 1967-May 1968 with director Orson Welles (Box 5)
      - Scripts (in Croatian) (Box 5)
    - Television series based on war diaries 1941-1947, 1960, 1967-1970, undated (Box 5)
    - Yugoslavia--the Land of Heretics, 1968-1969 (Box 5)
  - Books
    - The Battle Stalin Lost
      - Outlines, drafts, and research materials undated (Box 5)
      - Book reviews
        - In English 1970-1972, undated (Box 5)
        - In other languages 1969-1971, undated (Box 5)
    - Beliske iz Amerike
      - Outlines, drafts, and research materials
        - Notes, handwritten and typed undated (Box 5)
        - Hollywood Writers Mobilization 1944-1951 (Box 5)
        - Printed Materials 1943-1945 (Box 5)
    - The Beloved Land
      - Outlines, drafts, and research materials undated (Box 5)
      - Book reviews
        - In English 1961 (Box 5)
        - In other languages 1961 (Box 5)
        - Scrapbook (all languages) 1960-1962 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence 1960-1962 (Box 5)
    - The Road to Sarajevo
      - Outlines, drafts, and research materials
        - General
          - 1881, 1912, 1924-1927, undated (Box 6)
          - 1960-1964, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Printed Materials 1906-1925, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Stojadinovic, Dragisa
          - General, 2 folders (Box 6)
          - Serbia and Germany in the World War, 1935, 6 folders (Box 6)
          - Uprising in Toplica in 1916-1917 and General Kosta Pecanac, 1960 (Box 6)
      - Book reviews
        - In English 1966-1967, 1970 undated (Box 6)
        - In other languages 1965-1970, undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Correspondence
        - In English 1960-1968 (Box 6)
        - In Other Languages
          - 1953-1954, 1960-1961, undated (Box 6)
          - 1962-1968 (Box 6)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 6)
    - Tito Speaks
      - Outlines, drafts, and research materials
        - 1948 (Box 6)
        - 1952-1953, 1983 (Box 6)
      - Book reviews
        - In English 1953 (Box 6)
        - In other languages 1970, 1980-1982 (Box 6)
      - Illustrations by Mihelic (Box 6)
    - War Diaries
      - Outlines, drafts, and research materials 1943-1954, undated (Box 7)
      - Book reviews 1945 (Box 7)
      - Correspondence 1941, 1966 undated (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous Writings 1943-1987 (both published and unpublished)